Guide to the Marci Reaven Research Files on the Cooper Square Committee TAM.724
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marci Reaven Research Files on the Cooper Square Committee
1954-2015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Reaven, Marci, 1954-
TAM.724
6.5 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
The Marci Reaven Research Files on the Cooper Square Committee (dated, 1954-2015) contain Marci Reaven's research files for her New York University PhD dissertation on the history of citizen participation in New York City urban planning, which she completed in 2009. Reaven's files consist of primary and secondary source materials compiled on the Cooper Square Committee (CSC). They include records collected directly from the offices of the CSC, personal files of former CSC members Walter Thabit, Lois Dodd, Rita Lee, and Frances Goldin, and records related to community activism collected from other archives.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Marci Reaven in 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.022.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection are in the order in which they were received by the donor, and have been divided into four series based on groupings established by the creator. Materials in each series are arranged in roughly chronological order. Series I: Marci Reaven Files reflects research files assembled and arranged by Marci Reaven. Materials in Series II: William Thabit Cooper Square Committee Files, Series III: Lois Dodd Cooper Square Committee Files, and Series IV: Collected Publications were sent to Reaven separately and are maintained in the order in which Reaven received them.
Historical Note
Marci Reaven (1954- ) is a scholar of American history and urban planning. She completed a PhD in American history at New York University in 2009. Reaven collected a wide array of documents on the Cooper Square Committee (CSC) for her dissertation "Citizen Participation in City Planning, New York City, 1945–1975,"which focused on community organizations in New York's Lower East Side and prominently featured the role of the CSC. In support of her research, she collected primary source materials directly from regional archives including the New York City Municipal Archives, Long Island University, the Social Welfare Archives at the University of Minnesota, and the New York State Archives in Albany. She also collected documents directly from the Cooper Square Committee offices and from individuals involved with the CSC including Walter Thabit, Lois Dodd, Rita Lee, and Frances Goldin.
Related Materials
For more information about the organizational history of the Cooper Square Committee see the Cooper Square Committee Records (TAM 356).
Scope and Contents
The Marci Reaven Research Files on the Cooper Square Committee (dated, 1954-2015) contain Marci Reaven's research files for her New York University PhD dissertation on the history of citizen participation in New York City urban planning, which she completed in 2009. Reaven's files consist of primary and secondary source materials compiled on the Cooper Square Committee (CSC), an organization focused on affordable housing and community development in Manhattan's Lower East Side. Reaven's research files include records collected directly from the offices of the CSC, personal files of former CSC members Walter Thabit, Lois Dodd, Rita Lee, and Frances Goldin, and records related to community activism collected from other archives. These records document the Cooper Square Committee's involvement in campaigns for affordable housing, community health initiatives, and against urban renewal projects around Cooper Square between the 1950s and 1990s.
Research files assembled by Reaven are largely maintained in chronological files, and individual documents are annotated with source information. Files from Lois Dodd and Walter Thabit were given to Reaven by Dodd and Thabit and consist of personal files related to their organizing activities with the CSC.
Urban renewal -- Citizen participation.; Community organization.; Neighborhood planning.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); Low-income housing.; Tenants' associations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Cooper Square Committee
- Series I: Marci Reaven Research Files, 1954-2015
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains research files on the Cooper Square Committee assembled by Marci Reaven. Many of the documents are maintained in chronological files with annotations related to the original source of each document. Annotatios are written in Reaven's short-hand, and include the following sources: CSC stands for Cooper Square Committee; documents marked 4215 indicate the Walter Thabit Papers at Cornell University; RLee indicates files given to Reaven by Rita Lee; CHPC stands for the Citizen's Housing and Planning Council archive in New York City; SWA stands for Social Welfare Archives at the University of Minnesota; FGoldin indicates files given to Reaven by Frances Goldin, Weinberg or LIU relate to the Weinberg Collection at Long Island Univeristy, State Arcives relate to documents sourced from the New York State Archives in Albany, MA stands for New York City Municipal Archives; and City Society stands for the United Methodist City Society. Other files in this series relate to specific campaigns, committees, individuals, and organizations involved in urban planning and activism in the 1960s and 1970s.
  - Cooper Square Committee, 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Square Alternate Plan, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Square Committee, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - James Felt, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Cooper Square: Pilot Rebab Study, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Cooper Square Committee, 1963-1970 (Box 2)
  - Cooper Square Committee, 1971-1975 (Box 3)
  - Cooper Square Architect Selection, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Central Plaza and Vietnam, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Cooper Square Committee, 1976-2000s (Box 4)
  - Thabit, Walter: Writing and Biographical Materials, 1957-1979 (Box 4)
  - Cooper Square Chronologies by Walter Thabit, 2004-2005 (Box 4)
  - Church of all Nations, 1970-1972 (Box 4)
  - Citizens Housing and Planning Council, 1959-1961 (Box 4)
  - United Housing Foundation, 1958-1960, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Cooper Square Songs, 1964-1967 (Box 4)
  - Mutual Housing Associations, 1971-1990 (Box 4)
  - Antonio Pagan Aainst Cooper Square, 1990s (Box 4)
  - Joint Planning Council, 1980s (Box 4)
  - Cooper Square Committee Published Reports, 1969-2000 (Box 4)
  - Project Area Committee Information: General, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Alternate Plan For Cooper Square Campaign Ephemera, circa 1961 (Box 4, Flat-file-folder 4)
  - Goldin, Sally Ann. A Tribute to Frances Goldin, undated (Box 5)
  - Metropolitan Council on Housing. A Citizens Survey of Available Land, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Urban Renewal, 1955-1977 (Box 5)
  - Lower East Side Neighborhood Association (LENA), 1961 (Box 5)
  - Metropolitan Committee on Planning (METCOP), 1954-1960 (Box 5)
  - Cooper Square Committee Anniversaries, 1984-2015 (Box 5)
  - Bowery R-10 Zoning Fight (Walter Thabit Papers), 1967-1970 (Box 5)
  - Broome St. Expressway (Walter Thabit Papers), 1962-1965 (Box 5)
  - Citizen Participation, Lower East Side, 1959-1966 (Box 5)
  - Planners for Equal Opportunity (PED), 1966-1990 (Box 5)
  - Housing Policy, 1958-1978 (Box 5)
  - Advocacy Planning, 1965-1977, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Community Boards, 1966-1977 (Box 6)
- Series II: William Thabit Cooper Square Committee Files, 1973-1991
  This series contains the personal files of community planning activist Walter Thabit and relate to his work with the Cooper Square Committee. These files include materials on general Cooper Square Commitee organizing beetween 1980 and 1989, Cooper Square Commitee elections, and urban development campaigns.
  - Urban League Demo Project, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Bowery Planning, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Square Health, 1965-1973 (Box 1)
  - Glick Sponsorship, 1975-1982 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Square Elections, 1976-1991 (Box 1)
  - Cooper Square, 1978-1989 (Box 1)
  - Artworks Committee, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Jewish Association for Services for the Aged Fight, 1982 (Box 1)
- Series III: Lois Dodd Cooper Square Committee Files, 1973-1975
  This series contains the personal files of artist and Cooper Square Committee leader Lois Dodd. Her files relate to Dodd's participation in urban planning campaigns including her work with the Urban Development Corporation, which the Cooper Square Committee (CSC) attempted to gain as a sponsor in the 1960s and 1970s; the Project Action Commitee; and the Bowery Residence Committee. Organizing materials related to the Bowery R-10 Zoning Fight relate to the CSC's efforts to prevent rent increases in 1975, and documents on the Broome Street Expressway relate to organizing efforts between the CSC and Jane Jacobs to resist the contruction of the expressway.
  - Bowery Health Facility, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Finances and Tax Returns, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Urban Development Corp, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Project Area Committee Contracts, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Bowery Residents Committee, 1975 (Box 5)
- Series IV: Collected Publications, 1971-1981
  This series contains publications related to urban planning (1970s-1980s), which were collected by Rita Lee, a district manager for Community Board 2. Publications include reports and recommendatons from the New York State Charter Commission, neighborhood planning guides, and community planning handbooks.
  - Introduction to New York City's Community Boards, undated (Box 6)
  - Criteria for Delineating Community Planning Districts, 1966 (Box 6)
  - City Planning Commission. Community Planning Districts, 1967-1968 (Box 6)
  - Urban Action Task Force. Operation Better Block, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Lindsay, John. A Plan for Neighborhood Government, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Washnis, George. Little City Halls, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Shalala, Donna. Neighborhood Governance: Issues and Proposals, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Sutton, Percy. A Plan for Localized Government for NYC, 1972 (Box 6)
  - City Planning Commission. Neighborhood Planning in NYC, 1973 (Box 7)
  - New Responsibilities for Community Boards, circa 1976 (Box 7)
  - Preliminary Community District Map, Mayor's Recommendations, 1976 (Box 7)
  - NYSDEC Environmental Quality Review Act, Handbook for Local Government, 1976 (Box 7)
  - District Manager Booklet, 1977 (Box 7)
  - City of New York, Guides for Community Boards, 1977 (Box 7)
  - League of Women Voters. You and Your Community Board, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Community Board 2, Resource Directory, 1988 (Box 7)
  - Funding Need of NYC's Community Board, 1981 (Box 7)
  - State Charter Revision Commission. Expense Budget Under Decentralization, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Marshall, Kaplan, Sheldon Gans, and Howard Kahn. Charter Reform of NYC's Planning Function, 1973 (Box 7)
  - State Charter Revision Commission. Community Boards, 1974 (Box 7)
  - State Charter Revision Commission and Columbia University, Office of Neighborhood Government, 1974 (Box 7)
  - State Charter Revision Commission. Summary of Preliminary Recommendations, 1975 (Box 7)
  - State Charter Revision Commission. Preliminary Recommendations, 1975 (Box 7)
  - State Study Commission for New York City. Restructuring the Government of NYC, 1972 (Box 7)
  - State Charter Revision Commission. Final Report, 1975 (Box 6)
  - State Charter Revision Commission. Final Report, 1976 (Box 6)
  - State Charter Revision Commission. Charter Revision Guide for Community Board Members, 1976 (Box 6)
  - State Charter Revision Commission. Final Report to the Legislature, 1977 (Box 6)
  - State Charter Revision Proceedings, 1972 (Box 7)